Finding Aid for Allen H. Meyers Papers, 1935-1971
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Allen H. Meyers Papers 1935-1971
Meyers, Allen H., 1908-1976.
85285 Aa/2
Aviator and airplane designer, founder of Meyers Aircraft Company, Tecumseh, Michigan. Personal materials, business papers, biographical material, photographs and miscellanea; include letter from Howard Hughes, Sept. 10, 1947.
3 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mrs. Allen H. Meyers (donor no. 6179 ) and came to the library in 1978. Periodic additions were received.
The collection is open to research.
Allen H. Meyers was born in Allenhurst, New Jersey, in 1908. He early developed an interest in mechanics as a result of his father's training as a mechanical engineer. This together with the excitement generated by Lindbergh's flight inspired Meyers to choose a career in aviation. Because no university offered an organized curriculum in aviation at that time, Meyers decided to pursue an apprenticeship at the Stinson Aircraft Corporation of Wayne, Michigan. By the time he was 27, he had already constructed and tested a personal open-cockpit biplane, a new concept at that time. This plane became famous as the OTW (Out To Win). Meyers began manufacturing the OTW in Tecumseh, Michigan, in the late 1930's. The plane was later used in the Civilian Pilot Training Program during World War II.
Changes in technology during the war brought the period of the biplane to an end. After the war the Meyers plant began manufacturing aluminum boats while Meyers worked on the design of a new airplane. Production of the new plane, the Meyers 145, began in the early 1950's. It was followed by the Meyers 200, manufactured from 1959-1965, a four-place airplane with retractable tricycle gear, noted for its safety of design and its outstanding performance in races. In 1965, the design of the 200 was purchased by North American Rockwell. Meyers and his wife used the profits to establish the Meyers Foundation to support scientific research and development.
In 1974, Allen Meyers was inducted into the Aviator's Hall of Fame at the Glenn Curtiss Museum of Aviators at Hammondsport, New York. He died on March 15, 1976, and is survived by his wife, Dr. Nydia Luthy Meyers.
The Meyers papers include both business and personal material. Materials relating to Meyers' contributions in aviation are likely to be of interest to researchers. Included is correspondence from the 1930s through the 1951s with the Civil Aeronautics Administration concerning development of the OTW, 145, and 200. There is also extensive material relating to design, testing, and production of Meyers aircraft. The papers also may be of use to researchers interested in the fate of the small manufacturer. Those papers of a personal nature reflect Meyers' interest in fishing and in aviation as a hobby as well as business. In addition, the papers throw light upon social and political attitudes of the period. Of interest here is material concerning legal action against Mrs. Meyers, a former member of the Young Communist League, who was deported during the 1950s.
Subjects:
Aeronautics.; Meyers, Allen H., 1908-1976.; Tecumseh (Mich.)--Businesses.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Airplane industry--Michigan--Tecumseh.; Airplanes.; Airports.; Industrial buildings--Michigan--Tecumseh.; Interiors.; Laborers.; Meyers, Allen H., 1908-1976.; Meyers, Gladys.; Meyers Aircraft Company.; Submarines.; Tecumseh (Mich.)--Airplane industry.; Tecumseh (Mich.)--Industrial buildings.; World War, 1939-1945.
Contributors:
Hughes, Howard, 1905-1976.
Genre Terms:
Drawings.; Photographs.
- Biographical material
  - Clippings, etc. (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - Personal and business Undated, 1938-1971, 31 folders (Box 1)
  - Civil Aeronautics Administration, with 1934-November 1942, 14 folders (Box 1)
  - Civil Aeronautics Administration, with December 1942-1958, 12 folders (Box 2)
  - R.H. Draut, with, re. tests of OTW 1936-1946, 5 folders (Box 2)
  - D.G.A., Inc. 1947 (Box 2)
  - John Mann Airways, Inc. 1947 (Box 2)
  - A.R. Tiburzi 1954-1964 (Box 2)
- Business affairs
  - Design and Production
    - OTW
      - Tests, 3 folders (Box 2)
      - Stress analysis (chassis) (Box 2)
      - Landing gear, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Carburetor (Box 2)
      - Fin and rudder (Box 2)
      - Warner Scarab engine, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Kinner Motors, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Pilot training
        - Deliveries (Box 2)
        - Structural requirements (Box 2)
      - Owners (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Model 145
      - Placards (Box 2)
      - Plans for assembly, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Model 160, Conversion to (Box 2)
    - Model 200
      - "Basic Airplane Data" (Box 2)
      - Flight inspection report, 1 volumes (Box 2)
      - AC Spark Plug Division, 3 folders (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
    - Wheel castings 1935-1941 (Box 2)
    - Bowstring designs 1939 (Box 2)
    - Fuselage designs 1946-1947 (Box 2)
    - Ribs and outer panel designs 1947 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous drawings (Box 2)
    - Quality Control Manual, 1 volumes (Box 2)
    - Production planning meetings minutes
      - January-June 1947, 1 volumes (Box 2)
      - October 1959 (Box 2)
  - Finances
    - Journal (expenses) 1947 (Box 3)
    - Financial statements 1953-1955, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Sales 1962 (Box 3)
    - Audit report 1963 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - General
    - Minutes April 6, 1955-March 16, 1956 (Box 3)
    - Job cost analysis 1950 (Box 3)
    - Tecumseh airport (Box 3)
    - Progress report-aluminum boats (Box 3)
    - Purchase option agreement 1964 (Box 3)
    - Purchase orders (incoming) 1966-1968 (Box 3)
    - Publicity, 5 folders (Box 3)
    - Clippings (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 3)
- Personal
  - Diary 1943 (Box 3)
  - Diary 1967 (Box 3)
  - Ledger with autobiographical notes (Box 3)
  - Arctic Fly-In Diary 1970, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Tax information (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Mrs. Nydia Luthy Meyers
    - Vita, deportation case, and miscellaneous (Box 3)
    - Correspondence with Dan H. McCullough (attorney) (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 3)
- Photographs
  - Airplanes
    - Construction, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Meyers OTW (Box 3)
    - Meyers 02 (Box 3)
    - Meyers 145 (Box 3)
    - Meyers 200 (Box 3)
    - RAF 15 Airfoil (Box 3)
    - Tests (Box 3)
    - Warner Scarab Engine (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Boats (Meyers Aircraft product) (Box 3)
  - Jeep Enclosures (Meyers Aircraft product) (Box 3)
  - Meyers, Allen and Gladys (Box 3)
  - Meyers Aircraft Company
    - Exterior (Box 3)
    - Interior (Box 3)
  - People, Unidentified (Box 3)
  - People, Unidentified, with airplanes (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
    (includes photo of U-boat on display in Tecumseh, Michigan, 1943?)